American Philosophical Society Archives. Record Group IIa. 1743-1806 APS.Archives.IIa APS.Archives.IIa
American Philosophical Society
- Papers
  - Subscription List of Philadelphia Merchants. Proposal for Opening a Canal between the Delaware River and the Chesapeake, American Philosophical Society. Art.
  - Letter to Tho[ma]s Bond, April 25, 1769; 9x7-1/4; Gale, Benjamin, 1715-1790
    Killingworth, A.L.S. 3p.and end. Donates two examples of Abel Buel's printing types to the APS. See Minutes, June 16, 1769, p.39.
  - Account of the expenses and disbursements of the committee for examining the canal, June 16, 1769; 9x7-1/2; American Philosophical Society
    D. 2p.and end. See Minutes, pp.39-40.
  - Elevation between Bohemia and Apoquinimy rivers, together with estimate of expense of making a canal, June 16, 1769; 41-1/2x7-1/4; American Philosophical Society
    D. 1p. Part of report of canal committee. See Minutes, pp.39-40.
  - Report to the Society of proposals for increasing the cabinet, April 20, 1770; 12x7-1/2; American Philosophical Society. Curators
    D.S.: Isaac Bartram, Benjamin Rush and Owen Biddle. 2p. See printed Minutes, pp. 53-54.
  - Letter to the General Assembly of Pennsylvania, Sept. 20, 1770; 12-1/2x7-1/2; American Philosophical Society
    Philadelphia, L. 1p.and end. Copy. Presents Transactions. For report of this letter, see Minutes, p.58.
  - Account with the American philosophical society, Feb. 22, 1771; 9-3/4x9; Bradford, William, 1719-1791
    D.S.: Wm.and Thos.Bradford. 1p.and end.
  - Bill to the American philosophical society for binding 500 volumes of the Transactions, Feb., 1771; 8-1/2x8; Taylor, Samuel
    D. 1p.and end.
  - Letter to [William] Smith, June 6, 1771; 8-1/2x7-1/4; Colden, Cadwalader, 1688-1776
    New York, A.L.S. 1p.and add.and end. Enc.wanting. Acknowledges election to membership. Encloses a paper.
  - Letter to the [American] philosophical society, Oct. 11, 1771; 8 1/2" x 10"; Society for the Encouragement of Arts, Manufactures, and Commerce (Great Britain)
    London, A.L.S: Samuel More, secretary. 1p. and add., end. Acknowledges Vol. [1] of the Society's Transactions, conveyed by Dr. Benjamin Franklin.
  - Letter to Thomas Bond, Oct. 18, 1771; 9-1/4x7-1/4; Wrangel, Carl Magnus, d. 1786
    Stockholm, A.L.S. 2p.and add.and end. Acknowledges election to the APS.
  - An account of the machine for weighing loaded wagons, Oct. 25, 1771; 12x7-3/4; Philadelphia County (Pa.). Commissioners
    D. 1p.and end. Extracted from the commissioner's Book of Minutes. Read before the APS; Dec. 6, 1771. See: APS Minutes, p.68.
  - Letter to [Owen Biddle], Oct. 26, 1771; 12-1/4x7-3/4; Jones, John
    A.D.S. 2p.and end. Account of a machine for working a number of scythes with a horse. Printed: APS Minutes, p.66.
  - Account of papers communicated to the APS, published agreeable to their order by the secretaries, Dec. 19, 1771; 12x7; American Philosophical Society
    D.S.: John Ewing. 2p.and end.
  - Presentation note the University of Aberdeen of vol. I of the Transactions, [1771]; American Philosophical Society.
    Note to the University Library of King's College, University of Aberdeen, Scotland to accompany a presentation copy of vol. 1 of the Transactions.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Oct.8, 1772; 13x8; Dunn, Samuel
    London, A.L.S. 1p.,add.and end. Donates "a Chart of the Stars..." Says B.Franklin will propose him as a member. See Minutes, p.81.
  - Letter to Robert Strettle(sic) Jones, secretary of the A.P.S, Oct. 27, 1772; 7" x 9"; Manning, James, 1738-1791
    Providence, A.L.S. 1p. and add., end. Acknowledges Vol.1 of the Transactions presented to the college in Providence.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Nov. 23, 1772; 12x7-1/4; Howell, Rednap
    Boutetourte county, Virginia, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. Enc.of 3p. Concerning various inventions of his: e.g., time piece for ascertaining longitude at sea, and ship pump.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Dec. 29, 1772; 12x7-1/2; Leacock, John, 1729-1802
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Trade, navigation, etc., no. 5.) Asks for help in his project of wine making. Enclosed originally in letter from Leacock to T. Coombe;Dec.29, 1772. Cf. Minutes, p.75.
  - Letter to Thomas Coombe, Philadelphia, Dec. 29, 1772; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Leacock, John, 1729-1802
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. (see Ms.Comm.to the APS. Trade, navigation, etc., no.5.) Asks a favor. Encloses letter by John Leacock to the APS; Dec. 29, 1772.
  - Letter to Thomas Bond, Dec. 31, 1772; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Farmer, Ferdinand
    A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. Encloses pamphlet on parallax by Christian Mayer. Cf. Minutes, p.75.
  - Letter to Benjamin Franklin, Pres. of A.P.S., 1772; 7 1/4" x 9"; Forster, Johann Reinhold, 1729-1798
    No. 2 Sommerset house [ca.]. A.L.S. 1p. and add., end. Presents to the A.P.S. his translations of Kalm's Travels, Bossu's Travels, and Catalogues of North American animals, American plants, and Centuria of new insects. Cf. Minutes May 1,1772. Date is before July when F. joined Cooks's expedition.
  - Abbe [Francois] Rosier to, 1773 January 24; 9x7; Francois, Rosier, Abbe
    Presentation note to the American Philosophical Society to accompany Rosier's donation of a copy of his work entitled Demonstrations elementaires de botanique. Paris, Printed L.with ms.P.S. 3p.and end. In French. Presents two volumes to the APS. Refers to Franklin and de Magellan. Cf. Early minutes, Sept.17,1773. p.83 of printed Minutes.
  - Description and computation of the Height of Catherine's Hill and of the Blue Mountains, Jamaica, 1773 February 15; 12-1/2x8; Gauld, George
    Paper by Scottish surveyor George Gauld to be digested for publication. Port Royal, A.D.S. 2p.and end. Cf. Minute, p.80.
  - Letter to [Hugh Williamson], Feb. 15, 1773; 9x7-1/2; Gauld, George
    Port Royal, A.L.S. 1p.and end. "I have sent you...Lorimer's Account of Chester River &c...and likewise the description of the Sea Coast of Florida..." Cf. Minutes, p.80. For letter from Lorimer to Gauld, see Aug.13,1772 (bound with 917.59: G23.)
  - Letter to ----, May 27, 1773; 13x8-1/4; Jones, John
    Indian River, A.L.S. 2p.and end. Describes bridge proposed to cross the Schuylkill. See Proceedings, XXII,pt.3,80.
  - Letter to William Smith and Robert Strettell Jones, June [13], 1773; 12x8-1/2; Fontana, Felice, 1730-1805
    Florence, A.L.S. 3p.and end. In Latin. Acknowledges work presented to the accademia di Firenzi by the APS. Describes the academy. Translated: Ms.minutes, 1769-1774. Printed: APS Proceedings,vol.90,no. 5,Dec.1946.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, June 30, 1773; 9x7; Reale accademia delle scienze di Torino
    Turin, D.S.: Conte Saluzzo. 1p.and end. In Italian. Thanks for publication and sends their publication in return.
  - Letter to the A.P.S. See under date August 28, 1773, 1773 August 18; Accademia delle scienze dell'Instituto di Bologna
  - Letter to the American Philosophical Society, Aug. 20, 1773; 14-3/4x9-1/2; Colles, Christopher, 1738-1816
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p. Concerning his steam-engine. For report on his engine, see: APS Minutes, pp.82-83.
  - Letter to [APS], Aug. 28, 1773; 7" x 10"; Accademia delle scienze dell'Instituto di Bologna
    Bologna, A.L.S: Sebastiano Canterzani, segretario. 1p. In Italian. Acknowledges Vol. 1 of Transactions.
  - Letter to William Smith, Dec. 6, 1773; 9x7-1/4; Oliver, A. (Andrew), 1731-1799
    Salem, A.L.S. 3p.and add.,end. Concerning his new theory of lightning and thunder storms. Intends to forward a copy for the APS Transactions.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Dec. 7, 1773; 9x7-1/2; Mazzei, Filippo, 1730-1816
    Richmond, A.L.S. 2p.and end. Refers to Franklin. Printed: APS Proc.,v.90,no.5,Dec.1946.
  - Account of a snow plough, Dec. 17, 1773; 13x8-1/2; Wells, Richard
    [received]. D. 1p.and end.on 2 sheets. Cf. Minutes, p.85.
  - Chart of minutes of meetings as found in "leather book, blue book, red book, rough;", Jan. 5-May 19, 1774-1780; American Philosophical Society
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Jan. 21, 1774; 14-3/4x9-1/4; Wells, Richard
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 4p. Regarding the construction of wells.
  - List of papers communicated to the APS previous to, Jan. Feb. 28, 1775, 1774; 12x7-1/4; American Philosophical Society
    D.S.: R[obertJ Strettell Jones. 3p.and end.
  - Extracts from his journal, volume C., March, 1774; 13x8; Morgan, John, 1735-1789
    Philadelphia, Typed D. 7p.and end. Refers to B.Franklin.
  - Letter to the Philosophical society of Philadelphia [sic], April 12, 1774; 12-1/2x8; Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent, 1743-1794
    Paris, L.S. 2p.and end. In French. Presents publication. Printed: Duveen & Klickstein. Annals of science, v.11,no.12,plate 4-5.
  - Letter to Ferdinand Farmer, May 4, 1774; 9x6-1/2; Mayer, Christian, 1719-1783
    Manheim, L. 1p. Extract. In Latin. Forwards astronomical publications to the APS.
  - List of persons to whom books were to be sent by Dr. Franklin, 1774; 8x6-1/2; American Philosophical Society
  - Memoire instructif sur la maniere de conserverles oiseaux et autres objets d'Histoire naturelle, 1774; 13x8; Buffon, Georges Louis Leclerc, comte de, 1707-1778
    envoyé par M. Daubenton le jeune de la part de M. Le Comte de Buffon au Docteur Franklin pour etre Communique a la Societé Philosophique americaine etablie a Philadelphie; [ca.] Photo.of D. 2p. In French. (from original in the Library Company of Philadelphia.)
  - Letter to Thomas Bond, Jan. 16, 1775; 9x7-1/4; Normandie, John H. de
    Pa., A.L.S. 1p.,add.and end. Encloses copyu of letter from Lord Stanhope acknowledging election to membership of his father [Lord Mahon] and self.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, May 27, 1775; 9x7-1/2; Dicquemare, M. l'abbé (Jacques-François), 1733-1789
    Havre de Grace, A.L.S. 3p.and end. In French. Presents his work on sea-anemones. Cf. Minutes, p.97.
  - Letter to Peter Miller, July 29, 1775; 13x8; Mayer, Christian, 1719-1783
    Mannheim, L. 2p. Copy. Concerning the state of Europe. Hopes to forward some of his astronomical observations to the APS.
  - Letter to [William] Smith, Sept. 25, 1776; 9x7-1/2; Madison, James, 1749-1812
    William and Mary College, A.L.S. 4p.,end. (see Ms. comm.to the APS. Math. and astronomy, vol. 1, no. 11.) Astronomical matters.
  - Letter to Chris[tophe]r Marshall, Nov. 1, 1776; 3 3/4" x 6 1/4"; American Philosophical Society
    Phila., Printed D. 1p. and end. Invitation to a meeting that evening.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, 1777; 12-1/2x7-1/2; Mayer, Christian, 1719-1783
    Mannheim, [ca.]. A.L.S. 4p.and end. In Latin. ----English translation of 4p. Acknowledges election. Account of his work at the astronomical observatory at Mannheim.
  - Letter to James Madison, July 7, 1777; 9-1/2x7; Page, John, 1744-1808
    Williamsburg, A.L.S. 20p.and end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Math. and astronomy. vol. 1, no. 13.) Concerning his observation of the transit of Venus of 1769.
  - Letter to David Rittenhouse, [Samuel] Duffield, and [Pierre E.] DuSimitiere, Sept. 7, 1777; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Smith, William, 1727-1803
    L.S.: William Smith and Th.Bond. 1p. and end. Concerning copperplates for the Transactions.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, April 24, 1778; 12-1/2x7-1/2; Mayer, Christian, 1719-1783
    Mannheim, A.L.S. 4p.and end. In Latin. ----English translation of 4p. Printed: APS Transactions, vol.2, 217-219: Barton's Memoirs of Rittenhouse, p.577.
  - Letter to [George Louis Leclerc Buffon], Sept. 15, 1779; 7-1/2x12; Smith, William, 1727-1803
    Philadelphia, Copy of L.S. 2p. and end. ----Duplicate copy. A.P.S. returns thanks for presentation of Buffon's Histoire naturelle des oiseaux. Mentions B.Franklin.
  - Letter to David Rittenhouse, Dec. 4, 1779; 7 3/4" x 12 1/2"; Page, John, 1744-1808
    Williamsburg, A.L.S. 2p. Mutilated. Relative to a meteor seen in Virginia, Oct. 31, 1779. Read before the A.P.S., May 2, 1783; printed in its Transactions, v.2,173,1786.
  - Notes of committee of the treasury [endorsement sheet only], April, 1780; 7-1/2x9-1/2; American Philosophical Society
    D. 1p.
  - Letter to [David] Rittenhouse, Philadelphia, Nov., 1780; 8x6; Madison, James, 1749-1812
    William and Mary College, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. Enc. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Math. and astronomy, vol. 1, no. 17.) Forwards thermometrical and astronomical observations. For enclosure see: [Madison] Thermometrical observations; [Nov. 1780].
  - Thermometrical observations at William and Mary College, 1780, Nov., 1780; 8x6; Madison, James, 1749-1812
    []. A.D. 2p. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 1, no.9.) Enclosed originally in letter form Madison to Rittenhouse; Nov. 1780.
  - Observations of the solar eclipse of, Oct. 27, Nov. 20, 1780; 8x6-1/2; Willard, Joseph, 1738-1804
    A.D.S. 3p. (see Ms.comm. to the APS. Math. and astronomy, vol. 1, no. 15.) Printed: Am. acad. of arts and sci., Memoirs, vol. I, 129. Enclosed originally in letter from the American academy of arts and sciences to Ewing; Nov. 20, 1780.
  - Letter to John Page, Jan. 16, 1780; 8" x 6 3/4"; Rittenhouse, David, 1732-1796
    Philadelphia, A.L. 1/2p. and end. Incomplete. Relative to a meteor [which was seen on Oct. 31, 1779, and which is supposed to have fallen on or near the Ouasiota mountains]. The complete letter is printed in the Transactions of the American philosophical society, v.2,p.175. It was read before the A.P.S. on May 2, 1783.
  - Letter to Joseph Reed, Feb. 15, 1780; 10-1/4x6; Washington, George, 1732-1799
    Morristown, Photo.of A.L.S. 2p.and end. (from original in the Boston Public Library) Acknowledges membership in the APS. Cf. Minutes, June 16, 1780, p.109. Printed: Writings, vol.18, 11-12.
  - Letter to Joseph Reed, Feb. 15, 1780; 11x8-1/2; Washington, George, 1732-1799
    Morristown, Typed copy of L. 1p. Printed: Sparks, Washington, VI, 466.
  - Letter to Lewis Nicola, April 26, 1780; 8-1/4x7; Husbands, Hermon, 1724-1795
    A.L.S. 5p.and add.,end. Description of the Appalachian mountain region, together with a theory of the earth,submitted for examination.
  - Report of committee with the committee from the Library company, May 19, 1780; 9-1/2x8; American Philosophical Society
    Philadelphia, D.S.: Th.Bond, William Smith, Josiah Hewes, and Mordecai Lewis. 1p.and end. Grants APS permission to hold meetings in the west room of the Library company building.
  - Concerning the growth of Plants, June 16, 1780; 11-1/2x7-1/2; Matlack, Timothy, 1736-1829
    [read] D. 13p.,end. (see Ms. comm.to the APS. Natural history, vol. 1, no. 1.) Cf. Minutes, p.109.
  - List of members in arrears, July 10, 1780; 11x9; American Philosophical Society
    D. 2p.and end.
  - Catalogue of officers, Aug. 30, 1780; 8x6-1/2; American Academy of Arts and Sciences
    elected [Nov. 20,], D. 1p. (see Ms. comm.to the APS. Math.and astronomy, vol. 1, no. 16.) Enclosed originally in letter from the American academy of arts and sciences to Ewing; Nov. 20, 1780.
  - Subjects for prizes, Sept. 5, 1780; 11-3/4x7-1/4; Académie des sciences, belles-lettres et arts de Lyon
    Lyons, D.S.: La Tourrette, Perpetual Secretary. 3p.and end. Subjects for prizes for 1782 and 1783, proposed by the abbé Raynal. For printed copy, see Broadsides, 207.
  - Letter to [James] Ewing, Nov. 20, 1780; American Academy of Arts and Sciences
    Beverly, A.L.S.: Joseph Willard. 3p.and end. by D.Rittenhouse. Enc. 9-1/2x8 (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Math. and astronomy, vol. 1, no. 14.) Concerning its formation. Concerning solar eclipse. For enclosure; see: Willard. Observations of solar eclipse...; [Nov. 20, 1780]; and, American academy of arts and sciences. Catalogue of officers; [Nov. 20, 1780].
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Dec. 15, 1780; 11-1/2x7-1/2; Nicola, Lewis, 1717-1807
    [read] A.L.S. 2p.and end. Scheme for philosophical committees throughout the continent to correspond with the Society.
  - Letter to the president of the A.P.S., Feb., 1781; 10" x 8"; Adams, Samuel, 1722-1803
    Phila., A.L.in 3d P. 1p. At the request of Mr. Bowdoin presents pamphlet in the name of the American academy of arts and sciences.
  - Notes upon papers read before, or submitted to, the American philosophical society, March, 1781; 7-1/2x6-1/2; Collin, Nicholas, 1746-1831
    D. 2p.and end. Read: March 16, 1781. Cf. Minutes, pp.111-112.
  - Letter to [Timothy] Matlack, March, 1781; 8-1/2x6-1/2; La Luzerne, Anne-César, chevalier de, 1741-1791
    A.L.in 3rd.P. 1p.and end. In French. Forwards list of prizes offered for 1782 by the academy at Lyons. Cf. Minutes, p.112.
  - Papers pertaining to the election of officers, Jan. 5, 1781; 13-1/2x8-1/4; American Philosophical Society
    D.S.: Geo. Duffield, Lewis Nicola and Du Simitiere, "Judges of ye Election." 3P.and end. See Minutes, Jan.5,1781, p.110, for list of officers elected.
  - Letter to the marquis de Lafayette, Jan. 27, 1781; 11-1/2x7; Matlack, Timothy, 1736-1829
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p.and end. Notice of his election to membership in the APS.
  - Letter to Major general de Granchain, Feb. 7, 1781; 11-3/4x7-1/4; Matlack, Timothy, 1736-1829
    Philadelphia, A.L.S.with initials. 1p.and end. Draft. Acknowledges for the APS the receipt of his observations upon eclipses. Cf. Minutes, 111.
  - Letter to [Timothy] Matlack, Feb. 15, 1781; 12-1/4x7-3/4; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert de Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834
    New Windsor, A.L.S. 3p.and end. Acknowledges election to the APS.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, Philadelphia, Feb. 16, 1781; 12x7-1/2; Sullivan, John, 1740-1795
    A.L.S. 2p. Donates fossil found near Portsmouth, N.H. See Minutes, p.111.
  - Plans for a rain gage, Feb. 19, 1781; 12-1/2x8; Nicola, Lewis, 1717-1807
    D. 2p.,end. (see Ms.Comm. to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 1, no. 10a.) For additional remarks, see letter from Nicola to ----; Feb. 20, 1781.
  - Letter to ----, Feb. 20, 1781; 12x7; Nicola, Lewis, 1717-1807
    Barrach, A.L.S. 2p.,end. (see Ms.Comm. to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 1, no. 10.) Additional remarks on a rain gage. For original paper, see: Nicola. Plans for a rain gage; [Feb. 19, 1781].
  - Letter to Timothy Matlack, Feb. 21, 1781; 12-3/4x7-3/4; Hazard, Ebenezer, 1744-1817
    Boston, A.L.S. 1p.and add.,end. Acknowledges election to the APS.
  - Letter to Timothy Matlack, Feb. 22, 1781; 8x6-3/4; Livingston, William, 1723-1790
    Trenton, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. Acknowledges elections as councillor of the APS.
  - Letter to [member of A.P.S.], Feb. 25, 1781; 6 3/4" x 8 3/4"; Chastellux, François Jean, marquis de, 1734-1788
    Newport, A.L.S. 1p. and end. Acknowledges election to membership. Cf. Minutes of March 16, 1781.
  - Notes on papers read before, or submitted to the American Philosophical Society, March 1781; Collin, Nicholas, 1746-1831
    Paper read March 16, 1781. Minutes, pp. 111-112.
  - Letter to Timothy Matlock, 1781 March; La Luzerne, Anne-César, chevalier de, 1741-1791
    In French. Forwards a list of prizes offered for 1782 by the academy at Lyons.
  - Letter to [member of the A.P.S.], April 18, 1781; 7 1/4" x 9"; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826
    Richmond, A.L.S. 1p. and end. Acknowledges election to the Council of the Society. Printed: A.P.S. Proceedings, v.87, no.3,1943,p.265.
  - Nouveau caractere d'ecriture dans le Gouvernement Anglais [Broadside], 1781; Fournier, Simon-Pierre, la jeune
    Broadside in French. See Ms. Comm. to the A.P.S.
  - Paragon, [ca. 1781]
    Broadside in French. This is printed on cloth. See Ms. Communications to the A.P.S.. It is with the Fournier le jeune material on printing.
    Broadsides.
  - Letter to ----, May 2, 1782; 9x7-1/4; Barbé-Marbois, Francois, marquis de, 1745-1837
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 1p.and end. Submits a letter from M.d' Abeville. For letter(?), see Minutes, p.114.
  - Letter to Thomas Bond, Nov. 4, 1782; 13x8; Stonemetz, George
    Philadelphia, L.S.: George and Jacob Stonemetz. 1p. and add.,end. (see Ms. comm. to the APS. Natural history, vol. 1,nos. 7-8.) ----Copy signed by Jacob Stonemetz. Concerning a supposed tea plant. Cf. Minutes, p. 116. See Manuscript Communications.
  - Letter to the secretary of the Literary society of the U.S. (sic), March 15, 1783; 6 3/4" x 8 1/2"; Court de Gébelin, Antoine, 1725-1784
    [Paris] A.L.S. 2p. and add. In French. Acknowledges election to membership. Presentation of his Monde primitif. Fete held by the Musée de Paris in honor of the peace; Dr. Franklin's attendance. Cf. Minutes of Sept. 26, 1783.
  - Report of curators concerning the state of the natural curiosities in the museum, April 2, 1783; 7-3/4x6-1/4; American Philosophical Society
    Philadelphia, D.S.: Samuel Duffield and Eben[ezer] Hazard. 1p.
  - Letter to the secretary of the A.P.S, June 17, 1783; 8X13; Magalhães, João Jacinto de, 1722-1790
    London, A.L.S. 2p.,add.and end. Presents a number of books to the APS. Wishes to become a member. Refers to Franklin several times. Printed: Pro., XXII, pt.3,118-119.
  - Letter to [the American philosophical society], June 27, 1783; 8x13; Bataafsch Genootschap der Proefondervindelijke Wijsbegeerte (Rotterdam, Netherlands)
    Rotterdam, L.S.: Lambert Buher, First Sec'y. 1p. and end. Donates a set of their Transactions to the APS. Sends set, also, for B. Franklin.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, July 12, 1783; 9x7; Mandrillon, Joseph, 1743-1794
    Amsterdam, A.L.S. 3p. In French. (tipped in, in: Mandrillon. Recherches philosophique...; 1783. 973.1:M31) (Letter removed July 1984 - now in A.P.S. Archives) Donates manuscript copy of his answers to the prize question of the academy of Lyons. Cf. Minutes, Feb.6,1784, p.122.
  - Letter to the American philosophical society, July 27, 1783; 9x7-1/4; Godefroy,
    Paris, A.L.S. 1p.and end. In French. Gives prints relative to the American revolution. Cf. Minutes, p.118. For prints, see in Print Collection.
  - Letter to Thomas Bond, Sept. 19, 1783; 11x8-1/2; Hopkinson, Francis, 1737-1791
    Philadelphia, Typed L. 2p. Printed in part: APS Transactions, v.II,183-185. Cf.Minutes,p.118. Presented by Glassboro State College, Glassboro,N.J.,from the Stewart Collection May 1960.
  - Letter to [William] White, Sept., 1783; 9x7-1/4; La Luzerne, Anne-César, chevalier de, 1741-1791
    Philadelphia, L.S. 1p.and end. In French. Louis XVI will accept Rittenhouse's orrery. Cf. Minutes, p. 118.
  - Book receipts, Oct. 17, Dec. 10, 1783; 6-1/2x3-1/2; Rittenhouse, David, 1732-1796
    A.D.S. 2p.
  - Tho[ma]s Bond to [John Hyacinth de Magellan], October 18, 1783; 8" x 13 1/4"; Bond, Thomas, 1712-1784
    Philadelphia, 2 pp. and endorsement. A.Dr. of L.S. Acknowledges receipt of letter of June 17, 1783, and books for A.P.S. Indicates that M. Magellan will be elected to membership in the Society. See Pro., XXII, pt. 3, 118-119.
  - Letter to the secretary of the A.P.S., Dec. 10, 1783; 9x7-1/2; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert de Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Paris, A.L.S. 1p.and end. Encloses pamphlet containing account of French balloon experiments. Cf. Minutes, p.125.
  - Report of the committee appointed to revise the constitution and laws of the society, Feb. 3, 1784; 13x8-1/4; American Philosophical Society
    D.S.: Fra[nci]s Hopkinson, John Morgan and Eben[ezer] Hazard. 3p.and end. Cf. Minutes, p.122.
  - Letter to David Writtenhouse [sic], Feb. 14, 1784; 9-1/4x7-1/2; Vaughan, Samuel, 1720-1802
    Philadelphia, A.L.S. 2p.and add.,end. Presents "valuable philosophical instruments" to the society. Cf. Minutes, p.123.
  - A.P.S Bond to Francis Hopkins, 1784 Feb. 20; American Philosophical Society.
    Bond note for Three Hundred Pounds from Francis Hopkinson to the American Philosophical Society.